这张图展示了最近的一份近地轨道太空垃圾调查
This chart shows a recent survey of satellites and space junk in low-earth orbits
左边竖列是制造垃圾的国家
listed by of a country responsible for creating it
第三名你可能没想到，中国竟然和俄罗斯、美国有一样多的太空垃圾
The third country might be a surprise to you, China has left almost as much debris as America and Russia
虽然他们的太空史没那么悠久
despite having a much shorter history in space
实际上这当中大多数来自于2007年的一次导弹试验
In fact most of this was from just one missile test in 2007
当时中国发射了一发动能弹头击毁了一颗已退役的卫星
when China fired a kinetic kill vehicle that one of its own retired weather satellites
击中时相对速度有每秒8千米
The missile hit at a relative speed of about 8 km/s
把卫星炸成900个大碎片和35,000个小碎片
shattering the satellite into more than 900 large pieces and almost 35,000 small objects
它们中绝大多数都会在轨道停留几十甚至上百年
many of these will remain in orbit for decades or even centuries
上次提起此事我当时还评论谴责了下中国的做法
Now the last time I mentioned China's 2007 missile test I got some flak in the comments for picking on China
但也没办法，这事其他好多国家也都干过
so yes other nations also have done similar things
产生的这些太空垃圾也是太空军备计划的典型产物
and its legacy of space junk is typical of early missions in many national space programs
上世纪五十年代国际普遍认为近地空间将是一个新的战场
In the 1950's global powers faced the likelihood that Low Earth Orbit would become the new battleground overhead
谁掌握了那里谁就能在未来战争中手握王牌
and control of that space will be a deciding factor in future wars
在1958年，中华人民共和国主席毛泽东同志决定发展太空计划
In 1958 Chairman Mao Zedong announced a plan to develop a space launch capability
从建造洲际导弹计划开始
from a country's ballistic missile program
然而中国和苏联关系在五十年代到六十年代早期逐渐恶化
However when relations between the Soviet Union and China cooled in the late 1950s and early 60s
苏联的技术团队也全都撤回
The Russian technical assistance also went away
也尽管中国在六七十年代经济发展缓慢
Although the Chinese economy grew slowly in the 60s and 70s
但中国的确成为了世界上第五个独立研制并发射卫星的国家
they did become the fifth nation to independently develop and launch their own satellite system
1970年4月，长征一号发射成功
with the long march one rocket in April 1970
接下来二十年中国的载人航天计划一直在搁置
Over the next two decades plans for manned space flight were put on hold
太空发射主要还是中国的卫星
but the space launches continued to deploy mostly Chinese satellites
实际上如今中国已经使用长征系列火箭发射258次，成功率94.6%
In fact today there have been 258 launches using the Long March family of rockets with a success rate of 94.6%
直到1992年，现代化的中国的领导者才再次看到太空计划的价值
It took until 1992 before the leadership of a modernized China saw value in a space program again
——刺激、促进工程、科学领域的高端技术发展
as a way to stimulate and demonstrate advances in engineering and science
1992年，921工程被提出，中国决定送人上太空
In 1992 project 921 was approved its objective to establish a manned Chinese presence in space
921的第一步是造能载人的飞船
The first step of a new program was to develop a human rated capsule
“神舟”号飞船在1999年11月进行了一次成功的无人试飞
'Shenzhou' meaning divine vessel flew a successful unmanned test flight in November 1999
两年后，神舟二号携带几只动物测试了生命保障系统
Two years later 'Shenzhou 2' - carried animals on board to test the life-support systems
包括猴子、狗、兔子、几只蜗牛
a monkey a dog a rabbit and some snails
尽管研发之路很曲折，但神舟五号还是在2003年10月15日上天了
Despite setbacks progress on Shenzhou developed steadily and on October 15th 2003
杨利伟，中国第一位进入太空的航天员
Yang Liwei, the first Taikonaut traveled on board Shenzhou 5
使中国成为第三个独立送人进太空的国家
making China the third nation to independently carry a human into space
汉语里的“太空”加上英语的naut，合起来就是Taikonaut
Now the Mandarin word for space is 'taikong' add the Western word naut and you have Taikonaut
中国版的“航天员”
the Chinese version of astronaut
杨利伟在太空呆了21小时，绕地球14圈
Liwei completed 14 orbits of the earth in a little over 21 hours
其间在相机前挥舞了中华人民共和国国旗与联合国国旗庆祝
celebrating by waving the flags of the People's Republic of China and the United Nations to the onboard cameras
921工程下一步是造一个小型空间站
The next phase of project 921 was to establish a small space station
2011年中国造了8.5吨的天宫一号
By 2011 for Chinese space agency had constructed and prepared the eight and a half ton tiangong 1 or 'Heavenly Palace'
允许三位航天员驻留几周的太空实验室
the Space Lab was capable of supporting three Taikonaut's for scientific missions up to a few weeks
内部涂有两种颜色，分别代表天和地
The interior was painted in two colors to represent the sky and the ground
帮助航天员在微重力环境下区分上下
helping the Taikonauts to orientate themselves in micro-gravity
天宫一号的主要目标是验证与神舟飞船的对接
However the main purpose of a prototype was as a target vehicle to test docking with the Shenzhou capsule
但当天宫一号完成了其最后一项地面测试后，中国航天出事了
but while the Tiangong-1 was completing its final ground tests the Chinese space agency faced a new problem
8月18日，长征二号丙火箭因二级发动机工作故障而发射失败
On August the 18th a Long March 2C rocket suffered a failure during the second stage engine burn and it was lost
如果相同的事情发生在天宫一号的发射、或者载人任务的发射上
If the same thing happened during the launch of a Tiangong-1 or a manned mission
那就GG了
it would be disastrous for the entire space program
工程师们在六个月内赶紧对长征二号进行了170多种改进
Engineers hurriedly made more than a 170 modifications to the Long March 2 in just six weeks
研发出的F-T1型终于能够发射中国的第一个空间实验室了
resulting in the new "FT-1" version which was approved to carry China's first Space Lab
2011年9月28日，天宫一号发射成功
On September 29th 2011 Heavenly Palace successfully launched into its target orbit
2012年6月，第一批三位航天员进驻，包括中国第一位女航天员刘洋
In June 2012 the first crew of three Taikonauts arrived including China's first woman in space Lu Yang
神舟九号成功与天宫一号对接，并驻留11天
The Shenzhou 9 spacecraft docked successfully and remained at Tiangong-1 for 11 days
在2013年第二批航天员返回后，天宫一号进入待机状态，轨道慢慢降低
After another man visit in 2013 Tiangong-1 was put into sleep mode and its orbit has been gradually decaying ever since
视频在YouTube发布的时候 天宫一号还没掉下来
现在它也差不多该落回地球了
But it's almost time for the first 'Heavenly Palace' to come back down to earth
2018年早期全世界几个航天机构都会追踪它
In the early months of 2018 the inter-agency space debris Coordination Committee will track
并且逐渐缩小再入大气时间的预测范围
the space labs reentry to further refine its prediction of where it might end up
提问 箭体上的“神箭”是谁写的？
2016年9月，第二个空间实验室，天宫二号
In September 2016 a second orbital lab Tiangong-2
在酒泉卫星发射中心发射，几个月后与载两人的神舟十一号对接
launched from the Jiuquan Launch Center in the Gobi Desert to be joined a month later by
two-man crew aboard at Shenzhou 11
天宫二号设计与大小和天宫一号很接近
With a similar size and design to the first Heavenly Palace
让航天员景海鹏与陈冬在上面停留了30天
Tiangong-2 - was able to support Taikonauts Jing Haipeng and Chen Dong for 30 days
其间他们测试了很多科学仪器
During this time they tested a range of scientific instruments
包括第一个空间冷原子钟
including the first ever cold atomic clock experiment in space
在比绝对零度高零点几度的温度工作
which operated at a fraction of degree above absolute zero
每百万年误差一秒
so accurate but it only loses one second every billion years
中国除了搞载人航天计划
As well as setting up an independent manned space program
还研究了几个新的高科技月球车
China is also breaking new ground with a serious high-tech moon Landers
2013年12月1日，1200千克的嫦娥三号着陆器发射前往月球
On the 1st of December 2013 a 1200 kilogram Lander named Chang'E 3 launched on a mission to the moon
五天后嫦娥三号进入100千米高的近月轨道
Five days after a launch Chang'E 3 entered an orbit approaching 100 km altitude above all in the lunar surface
在12月4日，第二次减速点火后
After a second decelerating burn on the 14th of December
着陆器缓缓下降至月球表面雨海的一百米高处
the lander descended to just a hundred meters altitude above the Mare Imbrium
悬停的同时，相机寻找合适的着陆点
hovering in position whilst it's onboard cameras located the clear landing site
12分钟着陆程序执行后
Executing a 12-minute landing sequence
嫦娥三号成功着陆，37年后月球表面又一次有人类的探测器来访
Chang'E 3 touchdowned successfully, the first lunar soft landing in 37 years
但任务才刚开始
But the mission was far from over
就像苏联在七十年代的月球车一样
Like the soviet Lunokhod rovers of the early 1970s
嫦娥三号装有核动力的发热单元，让其熬过月球上的漫漫长夜
Chang'E 3 was equipped with a nuclear-powered heating unit to survive the harsh lunar nights
除了各种科学仪器，中国的月球着陆器还有一个140千克的玉兔号月球车
As well as having an array of scientific instruments, the Chinese Lander also carried a 140 kilogram Rover called Yutu
它探索了着陆点附近的火山口
which explored the volcanic crater near the landing site
玉兔的名字来自中国的古老传说
The rover was named by public poll in Chinese mythology
玉兔是象征月亮的女神——嫦娥的宠物兔子
Yutu was the pet rabbit of Chang'E, the moon goddess
所以西方我们叫它“玉做的兔子”、“月亮兔”或者干脆叫“兔子”
so in the West we know the rover as the Jade rabbit, moon rabbit or just rabbit
但玉兔号在2014年1月发生了一点小故障
But this particular rabbit came to a bit of a sticky intermittent end in January 2014
据中国国防科工局说是“机构控制出现异常”
when it had a "mechanical control abnormality" according to the Chinese state media
西方普遍认为原因是月球上的尘土让机械部件出现故障
Although many in the West believe it fell victim to be highly unforgiving the lunar dust jamming its mechanics
玉兔后来断断续续的和地球有所联系
It intermittently communicated back again with earth up
百度百科上说是2016年7月31日停止工作的
直到2015年3月停止工作
until March 2015 when it finally fell silent
但中国说没玩够，2018年嫦娥三号的备份嫦娥四号要在月球背面着陆
But China aims to go even further in 2018 when the backup lander of a Chang 3 mission is scheduled to do a touchdown
on the far side of a moon as Chang'E 4
这可是很厉害的第一次
This will be an impressive first
因为之前美国和苏联的所有软着陆都在月球面向地球那侧
All the American and Soviet soft landings were executed in direct line of sight with the earth
计划着陆点在南极-艾托肯盆地
The proposed landing site is the 'South Pole-Aitken basin'
太阳系中已知的最大陨石坑，直径2500千米
a candidate for the largest impact crater in the solar system with a diameter of 2500 km
在那里，中国的着陆器可以研究月球暴露出的15千米的地壳
Here the Chinese Lander will be able to examine 15 kilometers of exposed crust
希望能找到些证据帮助我们了解月球那千疮百孔的过去
hopefully uncovering evidence to help us understand the moon's violent past better
2016年中国发射了22发火箭，比俄罗斯多，和美国一样多
In 2016 China launched 22 rockets that's more than the Russians and the same number as the US
中国在本世纪二十年代计划发射第三个空间站和一个太空望远镜
it has plans for a third space station and its own space telescope in the mid-2020s
并在三十年代中期登月
with aims to put men on the moon by the mid 2030s
目前看来NASA、ESA和太空叉在不久的将来会多一个不好对付的竞争对手
so it looks like NASA, ESA and SpaceX will have some serious competition in the near future
感谢观看，这期的衣服是在这家店买的
So thanks watching and this episode shirt was the Navy Paisley by
在下面这网站能买到，江浙沪不包邮
madcap England and is available form Atomretro.com with worldwide shipping from here in the UK
记得关注YouTube频道Curious Droid
Don't forget we also have the Curious Droid Facebook page and also
感谢所有充电投币点赞收藏关注的朋友们
like to thank all of our patrons for their ongoing support
感兴趣也可以关注UP主给虫，经常翻译一些科普视频
and if your interest in becoming patreon then you can find out more by clicking on the link now showing
再次感谢观看，记得点赞投币分享关注收藏
So once again thanks for watching and please subscribe, rate and share